帝
国
客
黑
装
重
上
阵
明天见
See you tomorrow.
我的天
Oh, my God!
我进来了
I'm in.
就快到了
We're almost there.
长官  你确定行得通吗
Sir, are you sure about this?
我说过不会有事的
I told you, we're going to be all right.
我知道  长官  只是
I understand, sir. It's just that...
附近的哨兵可不少
I'm scoping some serious sentinel activity up here.
-林克  -长官
- Link. - Yes, sir?
考虑到你的情况  我并不明白
Given your situation, I can't say I fully understand your reasons...
你为什么要自愿做我的接线员
for volunteering to operate onboard my ship.
但是  如果你想继续做下去
However, if you wish to continue to do so,
我需要你做一件事
I must ask you to do one thing.
什么事  长官
What's that, sir?
相信我
To trust me.
是的  长官  我会的
Yes, sir. I will, sir.
-我现在就相信你  长官  -希望如此
- I mean, I do, sir. - I hope so.
把主电源接到硬盘上  准备发射信号
Repatch the main AC to the hard drives and stand by to broadcast.
是  长官
Yes, sir.
还是睡不着吗
Still can't sleep?
想聊聊吗
You wanna talk?
只是做梦而已
They're just dreams.
如果你担心什么的话
If you're afraid of something...
我只希望
I just wish...
我希望我知道该做些什么
I wish I knew what I'm supposed to do.
仅此而已
That's all.
真希望我知道
I just wish I knew.
她会找你的  别担心
She's gonna call. Don't worry.
你们在这儿呢
Here you are.
-准备好了吗  -已经迟了
- Are we ready to go? - We're already late.
这些地热活动证实了
These geotherms confirm
奥西里斯号发来的最新消息
the last transmission of the Osiris.
机器正在向下挖
The machines are digging.
它们要从地表直接挖到锡安去
They're boring from the surface down to Zion.
-我擦  -这样会避开外围防线
- Mother... - They'll avoid the entire perimeter defense.
速度如何
How fast are they moving?
控制中心估测每小时一百米
Control estimates their descent at 100 meters an hour.
-现在有多深了  -接近两千米了
- How deep are they? - Almost 2000 meters.
-奥西里斯号的数据呢  -这数据肯定有误
- What about the scans from the Osiris? - They can't be accurate.
-也许是正确的  -不可能
- They may be. - It's not possible.
那样的话得有二十五万只哨兵
That'd mean there are a quarter-million sentinels out there.
-没错  -怎么可能
- That's right. - That can't be.
为什么不可能
Why not?
锡安的每位居民对应一只哨兵
A sentinel for every man, woman and child in Zion.
听着正像机器的逻辑
That sounds exactly like the thinking of a machine to me.
墨菲斯  你能来真好
Morpheus, glad you could join us.
奈奥比
Niobe.
我向大家道歉  但是想必大家都知道
My apologies to all. But as you are undoubtedly aware...
安全的传输地点越来越难找
it's become increasingly difficult to locate a secure broadcast position.
好地方都被乌贼占据了
Squiddies got our best spots.
主管线上全是它们
Main lines are crawling with them.
如果奈奥比说的没错
And if Niobe's right,
72小时后会有二十五万只
in 72 hours there's gonna be a quarter-million more.
我们该怎么办
What are we gonna do about it?
我们服从洛克指挥官的命令
We're gonna do what Commander Lock ordered us to do.
我们撤回锡安
We'll evacuate broadcast level and return to Zion.
指挥官有阻止
And does the commander
二十五万只哨兵的计划吗
have a plan for stopping 250,000 sentinels?
他正在拟定战略
A strategy is still being formulated.
当然了
I'm sure it is.
你认为我们该怎么做  墨菲斯
What do you think we should do, Morpheus?
-我们应该按照命令  -怎么了
- We should proceed as ordered... - What is it?
我不知道
I don't know.
但是  我需要请你们中的一位帮忙
however, I must ask one of you for help.
有人与我信念相同
Some of you believe as I believe,
有人则不同
some of you do not.
相同的人  应该知道这场战争即将结束
But those of you that do know we are nearing the end of our struggle.
预言很快就会实现  但是在那之前
The prophecy will be fulfilled soon. But before it can be...
需要先请示先知
the Oracle must be consulted.
如果现在返回充电
If we return and recharge now...
我们可以在36小时内回来
we can be back in 36 hours,
那时机器离我们还远
well before the machines reach this depth.
你知道你在要求什么吗
Do you understand what you're asking?
我在要求一艘船停在这里
I am asking that one ship remain here in our place...
以防先知联系我们
just in case the Oracle should attempt to contact us.
胡扯  你要有个人违抗直接命令
Bullshit. You're asking one of us to disobey a direct order.
没错
That's right, I am.
但大家都清楚  我们之所以在这
But we well know that the reason most of us are here...
正是因为我们的叛逆精神
is because of our affinity for disobedience.
那如果等你回到锡安
What happens when you get back to Zion...
指挥官要把你关起来  你又该怎么办
and the commander throws you in the stockade?
他不会的
He won't.
该死的  墨菲斯  你真是永远都不会变
Goddamn it, Morpheus, you ain't never gonna change.
我要留下来  看洛克[锁]怎么收拾你
Shit, I'll do it just to see what Deadbolt does to you.
给你36个小时
You got 36 hours.
我找尼奥
I'm looking for Neo.
-没听说过  -我有东西给他
- Never heard of him. - I have something for him.
一份礼物
A gift.
是他给了我自由
You see, he set me free.
知道了  滚吧
Fine, whatever. Now piss off.
-那是谁  -你怎么知道有人来过
- Who was that? - How did you know someone was here?
他给你留了这个
He gave you this.
他说你给了他自由
He said you set him free.
没事吧  长官
Is everything all right, sir?
会议结束了  快准备撤离
The meeting is over. Retreat to your exits.
-特工来了  -特工
- Agents are coming. - Agents?
快走
Go.
几位好啊
Hiya, fellas.
-是他  -系统里的另类
- It's him. - The anomaly.
-要上吗  -当然
- Do we proceed? - Yes.
-他仍然只是  -凡人而已
- He is still... - Only human.
升级了嘛
Upgrades.
-一切按计划进行  -没错
- That went as expected. - Yes.
跟以前一模一样
It's happening exactly as before.
也不尽然
Well, not exactly.
-刚怎么回事  -我也不知道  长官
- What happened back there, Link? - I can't figure it out, sir.
特工突然出现了
Agents just came out of nowhere.
然后出现了奇怪的代码  从没见过的加密方式
Then the code got all weird. Encryption I've never seen.
-尼奥还好吗  -哪是还好  你真该看看他
- Is Neo okay? - Okay? Shit, well guess you should've seen him.
他现在在哪
Where is he now?
他正像超人一样飞呢
He's doing his Superman thing.
你在哪呢
Where are you?
这里是尼布甲尼撒号
This is the Nebuchadnezzar on approach,
请求进入三号门
requesting access through Gate Three.
尼布甲尼撒号  这里是锡安控制中心
Nebuchadnezzar, this is Zion Control.
请保持目前速度  等待指示
Maintain present velocity and stand by.
收到  控制中心
Roger that, Control.
这里是锡安控制中心
This is Sion Control requesting
三号门立刻解除戒备
immediate stand-down of arms at Gate Three.
尼布甲尼撒号即将进入  开门
We have the Nebuchadnezzar on approach. Let's open her up.
尼布甲尼撒号  请从三号门进入  停在七号港
Nebuchadnezzar, you are cleared through Gate Three to Bay Seven,
收到  控制中心
Roger that, Control.
大门敞开  床也铺好了  欢迎回家
Door's open, bed's made. Welcome home.
回家真好
No place like it.
收到  控制中心
Roger that, Control.
控制中心  三号门关闭  请待命
Zion Control, stand by for Gate Three lockdown.
尼布甲尼撒号已停靠在七号港
The Nebuchadnezzar is down, Bay Seven,
收到
Understood.
米弗尼舰长
Captain Mifune.
墨菲斯舰长
Captain Morpheus.
你是来逮捕我的吗  舰长
Are you here to escort me to the stockade, captain?
-我只是来维和的  -洛克指挥官要你
- I'm just here to keep the peace. - Commander Lock demands...
请你立刻去见他  长官
requests your immediate counsel, sir.
-林克  -长官
- Link. - Sir?
做好尽快出发的准备
I want the ship ready to go as soon as possible.
明白  长官
Understood, sir.
-他们俩怎么回事  -墨菲斯和洛克吗
- What is it between them? - Morpheus and Lock?
-奈奥比  -奈奥比舰长
- Niobe. - Captain Niobe?
她以前跟墨菲斯在一起  现在跟洛克了
She used to be with Morpheus. Now she's with Lock.
怎么回事
What happened?
墨菲斯去见了先知  然后一切都变了
Morpheus went to the Oracle. After that, everything changed.
是啊  她有那个能力
Yeah, she can do that.
尼奥
Neo!
-天啊  -为什么他每次都知道
- Oh, no. - How does he always know?
他就没其他事可干了吗
Doesn't he have anything better to do?
大家都在说你救了很多人的命
You know what they say about the lives you save.
我可没救他的命
I didn't save his life.
你好  尼奥
Hiya, Neo.
-崔妮蒂  林克  -你好
- Trinity, Link. - Hey.
-你回来真是太好了  -谢谢  回来真好
- It's great to have you back. - Thanks. It's good to be back.
-我帮你拿吧  -不用  我可以自己拿
- Can I carry that for you? - No, I can carry my own bag.
-崔妮蒂  -不用了
- Trinity? - I'm fine.
-你可以拿这些  -当然  林克
- You can carry these. - Yeah, sure, Link.
你知道吗  明年我就可以上舰服役了
Hey, you know, next year I'm old enough to join a crew, right?
我一直在想这事  我决定了
I've been thinking a lot about it, and I've made my decision.
我猜猜看
Let me guess.
我想加入尼布甲尼撒号
I want to join the Nebuchadnezzar.
之前墨菲斯缺两个人
I know Morpheus hasn't filled the other crew position,
却只补了你一个  林克
except for you, Link.
我知道他有他的原因
I'm sure he has reasons...
但是越想  我就越觉得
but the more I think about it,
这是上天注定的
the more I think it's meant to be.
这是命运
You know, it's fate.
因为你我才在这里  尼奥
You're the reason I'm here, Neo.
我说过  是你找到的我  不是我找到的你
I told you, kid, you found me. I didn't find you.
我知道  但是你救我出来了  你救了我
I know, but you got me out. You saved me.
你救了你自己
You saved yourself.
-墨菲斯  -洛克指挥官
- Morpheus. - Commander Lock.
我和其他舰长谈过了
I spoke to the other captains.
我想给你次机会  解释你的行为
I wanted to offer you a chance to explain your actions.
我觉得我的行为不需要解释
I wasn't aware that my actions required any explanation.
你收到的直接命令
You were given an direct order...
-就是返回锡安  -我回来了
- to return to Zion. - I did.
但是你让一艘船留在那里了
But you asked for one ship to remain behind.
我想留在那里的  但是我需要回来充电
I would have stayed, but I needed to recharge my ship.
所以你承认你违背了你的职责
So you admit to a direct contravention of your duty.
指挥官  需要有人在矩阵里
Commander, we need a presence inside
等待先知的联络
the Matrix to await contact from the Oracle.
我不想听废话
I don't want to hear that shit!
我不关心什么先知  预言或者救世主
I don't care about oracles or prophecies or messiahs!
我只关心一件事
I care about one thing:
阻止机器部队摧毁这座城市
Stopping that army from destroying this city.
想成功  士兵就必须服从我的命令
And to do that I need soldiers to obey my orders.
请恕我直言  指挥官
With all due respect, commander,
只有一种方法可以拯救这座城市
there is only one way to save our city.
怎么拯救
How?
-尼奥  -该死的  墨菲斯
- Neo. - Goddamn it, Morpheus.
不是每个人都相信你那套
Not everyone believes what you believe.
我不需要他们去相信
My beliefs do not require them to.
今晚有个集会  大家都在谈这件事
There's a gathering tonight. Everyone's talking.
大家都很害怕
A lot of people are scared.
好久没有这么多飞船一起回来了
No one can remember the last time so many ships were docked.
有大事要发生了  是吗
Something is happening, isn't it? Something big?
我们不能说  别再问了
We're not allowed to say anything, so stop asking.
我的天  回家真好
Goddamn, it's good to be home.
我已经向议会提议  解除你的职务
I've already recommended to the council that you be removed from duty.
这是你的权利  指挥官
That is, of course, your prerogative, commander.
如果我能决定的话  你这辈子
If it were up to me captain, you wouldn't
都别想再上船了
set foot on a ship for the rest of your life.
那我很庆幸这不由你来决定
Then I am grateful that it is not up to you.
-哈曼议员  -指挥官
- Councillor Hamann. - Commander.
-舰长  -议员
- Captain. - Councillor.
议会让我在今晚神庙集会时发言
Council's asked me to speak tonight at the temple gathering.
飞船纷纷撤回
The presence of the fleet...
还有近来的谣言  需要给大家个解释
and the persistence of rumors must be addressed.
人民需要知道现在的情况
The people must be told what is happening.
当然  议员
Of course, councillor.
但请允许我提个建议
But might I advise a level
不要透露太多细节
of discretion concerning specific details.
-我们不希望造成恐慌  -没错
- We do not wish to start a panic. - Quite right.
谁都不想引起恐慌
A panic is not what anyone wants.
你怎么想  舰长  有何建议
What about you, captain? What would you advise?
真相  没人会恐慌的
The truth. No one will panic,
因为没有什么可怕的
because there isn't a thing to fear.
那支军队永远不会攻陷锡安
That army would never reach the gates of Zion.
你为什么这么肯定
What makes you so sure?
请想想最近发生了什么  议员
Consider what we have seen, councillor.
想想在过去六个月里
Consider that in the past six months...
我们救的人比过去六年还多
we have freed more minds than in six years.
这场进攻只是绝望之举
This attack is an act of desperation.
我相信  很快
I believe very soon
预言将会实现  战争也将终结
the prophecy will be fulfilled and this war will end.
我希望你是正确的  舰长
I hope you're right, captain.
预言成真不需要希望  议员
I do not believe it to be a matter of hope, councillor.
只需要时间
It is simply a matter of time.
我到了
My stop.
回见
See you soon.
希望别太快
Hopefully not too soon.
走吧  孩子  他们还有事要做
Let's go, kid. These two got things to do.
我们想的是同一件事吗
Are you thinking what I'm thinking?
你在想这电梯太慢了吗  我也是
I am if you're thinking this elevator is too slow.
-飞船充电要多久  -24至30小时
- How long do we charge the Neb? - 24, maybe 30 hours.
这可真是天大的好消息
Some people go their entire lives without hearing news that good.
尼奥  我儿子雅各布在诺西斯号上
Neo, please, I have a son, Jacob, aboard the Gnosis.
-请帮我照顾他  -我尽量
- Please, watch over him. - I'll try.
我女儿在伊卡洛斯号上
I have a daughter on the Icarus.
别走
No, wait.
没事  他们需要你
It's all right. They need you.
-但我需要你  -我知道
- I need you. - I know.
还有时间的
There's time.
我的妞...
Where's my puss...?
-你们好  -林克舅舅
- Hey! - Uncle Link!
上帝啊
God!
林克舅舅
Uncle Link!
我的天啊  你们长大了
Oh, my God! You're so huge!
-都能把我抱起来了  -不要
- You should be picking me up! - No!
-该你们了  -好吧
- Yeah! - Okay!
好吗  太好了
Okay? All right.
我们一起来  好吗
Now, we're gonna have to work together here, okay?
一  二  三  抬
One, two, three, lift!
我的天  你都喂他们吃什么啊
Oh, my God! What are you feeding these two?
孩子们  该走了
Come on, kids. It's time to go.
-你好  凯茜  -你好
- Hey, Cas. - Hey.
-你回来我真高兴  -我也很高兴
- Good to have you home, Link. - Good to be home.
小心点她
You be careful with her.
别担心我  要倒霉的是他
Don't worry about me. He's the one that's gonna get it.
走了  你们俩  走吧
Out the door! Both of you, march!
-再见  -再见
- Bye! - Bye!
我要倒什么霉
I'm gonna get what?
其他飞船回来的次数
Every ship up there's been home two...
是尼布甲尼撒号的两倍甚至三倍
even three times more than the Nebuchadnezzar,
别这样  姿怡  不是说好不谈了吗
Come on, Zee. I thought we were past this.
-你调去其他船我们就不谈了  -我办不到
- We'll get past this when you start operating another ship. - I can't do that.
-为什么  -你知道为什么
- Why? - You know why.
如果多泽知道我的感受
If Dozer knew how I felt,
他是不会要你这么做的
he wouldn't have asked you to do this.
也许吧  但是现在太迟了
Maybe. But it's too late now.
我做了承诺  有些承诺是不能反悔的
I made a promise, and some promises can't be unmade.
-这不公平  -没人说这公平
- It's not fair. - Nobody said it was gonna be.
我还活着  多泽却不在了
You think Cas thinks it's fair
凯茜觉得公平吗
that I'm here and Dozer's not?
我两个兄弟死在了那艘船上  林克
I lost two brothers to that ship, Link.
我很害怕
I'm afraid of it.
我怕你也回不来了
I'm afraid it's gonna take you too.
不会的
It won't.
你怎么知道
How can you say that to me?
因为有墨菲斯
Because of Morpheus.
因为他告诉过我
Because of what he's told me.
他说过  这一切快结束了
He said that this is it, that it will be over soon.
-林克  墨菲斯疯了  -是疯了
- Link, Morpheus is crazy. - No doubt.
但坦克和多泽相信他  我跟你说
But Tank and Dozer believed him. And I'll tell you what...
至从上了那艘船
after being on that ship
亲眼目睹尼奥所做的一切
and seeing Neo do the things he can do...
我必须承认
I gotta say,
我也开始相信他了
I'm starting to believe him too.
万事小心  林克
Be careful, Link.
一定要小心
Please be careful.
开始了吗
They started yet?
哈曼议员在作开场致辞
Only Councillor Hamann's opening prayer.
今晚  让我们向这些人致敬
Tonight, let us honor these men and women.
他们是我们的战士  英雄
These are our soldiers, our warriors.
他们是我们的丈夫和妻子  兄弟和姐妹
These are our husbands and wives, our brothers and sisters,
我们的孩子
our children.
让我们铭记逝去的人
Let us remember those that have been lost
感激幸存下来  站在我们身边的
and let us give thanks for those that have been found
各位勇士们
and who stand here beside us.
我想让一个人致最后的开场辞
Now I would like someone else to close this prayer.
他很久没在这里发言了
Someone who hasn't spoken here in a long time.
但我相信他的话
But who I believe has something to say
大家都要听一下
that we all need to hear.
有请墨菲斯
I give you Morpheus.
锡安  听我说
Zion! Hear me!
你们听说的都是事实
It is true what many of you have heard.
此时此刻  机器已集结了一支军队
The machines have gathered an army, and as I speak
正慢慢逼近我们
that army is drawing nearer to our home.
相信我  我们正面临艰难的时刻
Believe me when I say we have a difficult time ahead of us.
要准备好应对他们
But if we are to be prepared for it,
就必须抛弃心中的恐惧
we must first shed our fear of it.
我站在这里毫无畏惧
I stand here before you now truthfully unafraid.
为什么
Why?
因为有不同的信念吗
Because I believe something you do not?
不
No!
我之所以无畏  是因为我记得
I stand here without fear because I remember.
我记得  我能活到现在
I remember that I am here
不是因为前面的征途
not because of the path that lies before me
而是因为我走过的路
but because of the path that lies behind me.
我记得我们与机器抗争了百余年
I remember that for 100 years we have fought these machines.
这百余年来
I remember that for 100 years
它们不断派军队  企图消灭我们
they have sent their armies to destroy us.
经过一个世纪的抗争
And after a century of war,
我只记得最重要的一件事
I remember that which matters most:
我们依然屹立在这
We are still here!
今晚
Tonight.
我们要告诉敌人
Let us send a message to that army.
今晚  我们要尽情狂欢
Tonight, let us shake this cave.
今晚  让这恢弘的大厅
Tonight, let us tremble these halls
为我们颤抖
of earth, steel and stone.
让我们的呐喊从地心直冲云霄
Let us be heard from red core to black sky.
今晚  要让它们记住
Tonight, let us make them remember:
这就是锡安  我们无所畏惧
This is Zion and we are not afraid!
我记得
I remember.
我记得你以前爱跳舞
I remember you used to dance.
而且跳得不错
I remember you were pretty good.
奈奥比舰长  这个世上有些事
There are some things in this world, Captain Niobe,
是不会变的
that will never change.
奈奥比
Niobe!
但有些事会变的
Some things do change.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
-我想你  -我知道
- I missed you. - I can tell.
我在想  大家都在这
I was thinking, everyone is here.
跟我来
Follow me.
尼奥  怎么了
Neo, what is it?
哪里不对劲
What's wrong?
没事的  你可以跟我说
It's okay, you can tell me.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
别害怕
Don't be afraid.
我不能失去你
I can't lose you.
你不会失去我的
You're not gonna lose me.
感觉得到吗
You feel this?
我永远不会放手
I'm never letting go.
晚安  锡安
Good night, Zion.
好梦
Sweet dreams.
-你没事吧  -我没事
- You all right? - I'll make it.
你看到那个特工了吗  真是厉害
Did you see that agent? I've never seen anything like that.
那不重要  重要的是这个
It doesn't matter. All that matters is this.
你先
You first.
-天啊  -叫我史密斯就好
- Oh, God. - "Smith" will suffice.
-谢谢  -不客气
- Thank you. - My pleasure.
-要一起吗  -哈曼议员
- Care for some company? - Councillor Hamann.
如果你想一个人  我就不打扰了
I don't want to intrude if you'd prefer to be alone.
-不  有人一起挺好的  -很好
- No, I could probably use some company. - Good.
我也这么想
So could I.
今晚真美
It's nice tonight.
非常平静
Very calm.
感觉所有人都睡得很安稳
It feels like everyone is sleeping very peacefully.
并不是所有人
Not everyone.
我讨厌睡觉  一般只睡几个小时
I hate sleeping. I never sleep more than a few hours.
我十一岁前睡太多了
I figure I slept the first
现在要好好补偿睡过去的时光
11 years of my life, now I'm making up for it.
-你呢  -我总是睡不好
- What about you? - I just haven't been able to sleep much.
-这是好事  -为什么
- It's a good sign. - Of what?
证明你还是个人类
That you are in fact still human.
你去过工程层吗
Have you ever been to the engineering level?
晚上我喜欢到去那散步  感觉很棒
I love to walk there at night. It's quite amazing.
-想去看看吗  -当然
- Would you like to see it? - Sure.
基本没人会下来
Almost no one comes down here.
除非出问题了
Unless, of course, there's a problem.
人就是这样
That's how it is with people.
不出问题  就没人在意
Nobody cares how it works as long as it works.
我喜欢来这里
I like it down here.
这里提醒着我
I like to be reminded
这座城市的运转  全靠这些机器
this city survives because of these machines.
这些机器维持着我们的生命
These machines are keeping us alive
其他机器却要消灭我们
while other machines are coming to kill us.
有趣吧  可以给予生命
Interesting, isn't it? The power to give life
-也可以结束生命  -我们也一样
- and the power to end it. - We have the same power.
我们确实也是  不过
Yeah, I suppose we do, but...
有时候我会想起
sometimes I think about
那些还跟矩阵连着的人
all those people still plugged into the Matrix.
当我看着这些机器时
And when I look at these machines...
没法不去想
I can't help thinking that,
我们跟这些机器也连着
in a way, we are plugged into them.
是我们控制着机器  不是机器控制我们
But we control these machines, they don't control us.
当然  它们怎么可能控制我们
Of course not. How could they?
这就是胡扯
The idea is pure nonsense.
但我还是不禁会想
But it does make one wonder just...
什么是控制
what is control?
只要我们想  我们就可以把机器关掉
If we wanted, we could shut these machines down.
是啊  说得好  这就是控制
Of course. That's it. You hit it. That's control, isn't it?
只要我们想  砸个稀巴烂也行
If we wanted, we could smash them to bits.
不过我们还是得考虑
Although if we did, we'd have to consider
没有了光  热和空气
what would happen to our lights,
我们会怎样
our heat, our air.
我们需要它们  它们也需要我们
So we need machines and they need us.
您是要说这个吗  议员
Is that your point, Councillor?
不  不是
No. No point.
我这样的老头子
Old men like me don't
说话没那么多的目的性
bother with making points. There's no point.
所以没有年轻人在议会吗
Is that why there are no young men on the Council?
说得好
Good point.
告诉我你在想什么吧  议员
Why don't you tell me what's on your mind, Councillor.
这世上  有很多事情
There is so much in this world...
我都搞不懂
that I do not understand.
看到那台机器吗
See that machine?
好像是用来处理水循环的
It has something to do with recycling our water supply.
我压根不知道是怎么运作的
I have absolutely no idea how it works.
但我却明白它运作的原因
But I do understand the reason for it to work.
我也完全不明白
I have absolutely no idea how
为什么你能做那么多事
you are able to do some of the things you do.
但我相信  这也是有原因的
But I believe there's a reason for that as well.
我只希望趁来得及  快弄清楚
I only hope we understand that reason before it's too late.
-巴拉德  -他在吗
- Ballard. - Is he here?
尼奥  这是先知给的
Neo, it's from the Oracle.
该出发了
It's time to go.
墨菲斯早就说会是这样
Morpheus said this was how it was gonna happen.
预言可真可假  这说不好
I don't know. Maybe the prophecy's true, maybe it's not.
我只知道  飞船需要一个接线员
All I know is, that ship needs an operator.
也就是我
Right now, that operator's me.
我懂
I know.
-姿怡  -我希望你戴着它
- Zee... - I want you to wear it.
-你知道我不信这个的  -但我信
- You know I don't believe in this stuff. - But I do.
它总给我带来好运
It's always brought me luck.
也许能把你带回来
Maybe it'll bring me you.
我会回来的
I'm coming back.
我保证  无论如何我都会回来的
I promise. No matter what it takes, I'm coming home.
带在身边吧
Just keep it with you. Please.
为了我
For me.
好吧
Okay.
-尼奥  -怎么回事
- Neo! - How the hell...?
贝恩
Bane.
发生什么事了
Is something wrong?
没有  我很好
No, I'm fine.
我只是想赶在你离开前说句
I just wanted to catch you to say...
祝你好运
good luck.
谢谢
Thanks.
回见
We'll see you.
尼奥  时间刚刚好
Neo! Just in time.
-你要去见先知吗  -时间不多了
- You're gonna see the Oracle? - We don't have time.
抱歉  我有个东西要给尼奥
Sorry, sir. I just had to give something to Neo.
一个孤儿送你的礼物
A gift from one of the orphans.
他要我在你走之前交给你
He made me swear to get it to you before you left.
他说你看了就明白
He said you'd understand.
谢谢
Thanks.
我听说你允许尼布甲尼撒号起飞了
I was just told you cleared the Nebuchadnezzar for takeoff.
是的
That is correct.
议员  我们的防御系统还由我控制吗
Councillor, am I still in charge of our defense system?
当然
Of course.
我坚信  要想赢
I believe I need every ship
留下的飞船越多越好
we have if we're going to survive this attack.
这我明白  指挥官
I understand that, commander.
那你为什么允许尼布甲尼撒号离开
Then why did you allow the Nebuchadnezzar to leave?
因为我相信  我们的存活
Because I believe our survival
不仅取决于船的多少
depends on more than how many ships we have.
要小心
Be careful.
你好
Hello.
-你在找先知  -你是谁
- You seek the Oracle. - Who are you?
我是赛拉弗[炽天使]  我可以带你见她
I am Seraph. I can take you to her,
但我要先道个歉
but first I must apologize.
为什么道歉
Apologize for what?
为了这个
For this.
很好
Good.
先知有很多敌人  我得先弄清楚
The Oracle has many enemies. I had to be sure.
-弄清什么  -你就是救世主
- Of what? - That you are the One.
你可以直接问我
You could have just asked.
不  古话说  不打不相识
No. You do not truly know someone until you fight them.
来吧  她在等你
Come. She's waiting.
他们去哪了
Where the hell did they go?
这些是后门  对吧
These are back doors, aren't they?
程序员入口
Programmer access.
怎么运作的
How do they work?
代码都藏在锁里
A code is hidden in tumblers.
在这打开一把锁
One position opens a lock
别处会打开一扇门
and another position opens one of these doors.
你是程序员吗
Are you a programmer?
那你是什么人
Then what are you?
我保护着最重要的事物
I protect that which matters most.
过来吧  我又不会吃了你
Well, come on. I ain't gonna bite you.
过来让我好好看看
Come around here and let me have a look at you.
我的天啊  看看你
My goodness, look at you.
救世主当得还不错嘛
You turned out all right, didn't you?
-感觉怎样  -我
- How do you feel? - I...
我知道你经常失眠  一会说
I know you're not sleeping. We'll get to that.
过来这里坐坐吧
Why don't you come and have a sit this time.
-我站着就好  -你随便吧
- Maybe I'll stand. - Well, suit yourself.
-我想坐着  -我知道
- I felt like sitting. - I know.
好了
So.
不说摆在台面上的事了
Let's get the obvious stuff out of the way.
你不是人类  对吗
You're not human, are you?
再明显不过了
It's tough to get any more obvious than that.
我猜
If I had to guess,
你是机器世界里的一个程序
I'd say you're a program from the machine world.
-他也是  -猜得不错嘛
- So is he. - So far, so good.
如果这是真的  你也是系统的一部分
But if that's true, that could mean you're part of this system,
另一种控制程序
another kind of control.
继续
Keep going.
最显而易见的问题是
I suppose the most obvious question is...
-我怎么能相信你  -问得好
- how can I trust you? - Bingo.
这问题很难解释
It is a pickle, no doubt about it.
坏消息是  你没法知道
Bad news is there's no way if you can
我是不是在帮你
really know whether I'm here to help you or not.
这都取决于你
So it's really up to you.
你自己决定  是接受我的意见
Just have to make up your own damn mind
还是拒绝我的意见
to either accept what I'm going to tell you or reject it.
吃糖吗
Candy?
你知道我会不会吃吗
Do you already know if I am going to take it?
要是不知道  我还算什么先知
Wouldn't be much of an oracle if I didn't.
如果你早就知道了  我还怎么选择
But if you already know, how can I make a choice?
你不是来这里选择的
Because you didn't come here to make the choice.
你已经选好了
You've already made it.
你是为了弄明白  为什么要那样选
You're here to try to understand why you made it.
我还以为你早弄明白了
I thought you'd have figured that out by now.
-你为什么来这  -一样的理由
- Why are you here? - Same reason.
我爱吃糖
I love candy.
为什么帮我们
But why help us?
我们都在做自己该做的事
We're all here to do what we're all here to do.
我只对未来感兴趣  尼奥
I'm interested in one thing, Neo: The future.
相信我  想看到未来  就要团结
And believe me, I know, the only way to get there is together.
-还有像你一样的程序吗  -倒不会像我  但
- Are there other programs like you? - Well, not like me, but...
看到那些鸟了吗
Look. See those birds?
可以这样说  有个程序负责它们
At some point, a program was written to govern them.
树木和风  日出日落
A program was written to watch over the trees and the wind,
都有程序负责
the sunrise and sunset.
到处都有程序负责
There are programs running all over the place.
所有的程序各司其责
The ones doing their job,
干着自己该做的事  你看不到
doing what they were meant to do, are invisible.
你觉察不到它们的存在  可是其他的
You'd never even know they were here. But the other ones...
你每天都能听说
Well, you hear about them all the time.
-我从没听说过  -当然有
- I've never heard of them. - Of course you have.
每次你听到别人说
Every time you've heard someone say
看见鬼魂或者天使
they saw a ghost or an angel.
听到什么
Every story you've ever
吸血鬼  狼人或者外星人的故事
heard about vampires, werewolves or aliens...
都是有程序做了不该做的事
is the system assimilating some program...
系统在处理异常
that's doing something they're not supposed to be doing.
程序互相入侵
Programs hacking programs.
-为什么  -他们有自己的原因
- Why? - They have their reasons...
不过通常  要被删除的程序
but usually a program chooses exile
才会选择流亡
when it faces deletion.
为什么程序会被删除
And why would a program be deleted?
也许程序崩溃了
Maybe it breaks down.
也许有更好的程序替代它
Maybe a better program is created to replace it.
这种事很常见
Happens all the time.
这个时候
And when it does,
程序可以躲在这里
a program can either choose to hide here...
也可以回到源头
or return to the source.
-机器的主机  -没错
- The machine mainframe. - Yes.
一个你非去不可的地方
Where you must go.
救世主之路的尽头  你在梦里
Where the path of the One ends. You've seen it...
见到过  是吧
in your dreams, haven't you?
一道光芒四射的门
A door made of light?
你穿过那道门时发生了什么
What happens when you go through the door?
我看到了崔妮蒂
I see Trinity...
发生了件事
and something happens...
一件坏事
something bad.
她开始下落  然后我醒了
She starts to fall, and then I wake up.
-你看到她死了吗  -没有
- Do you see her die? - No.
尼奥  你有洞察未来的能力
You have the sight now, Neo.
这个世界在你眼里没有时间限制
You are looking at the world without time.
那我为什么看不到她到底怎样了
Then why can't I see what happens to her?
自己都无法理解的选择
We can never see past the choices
我们永远看不到结果
we don't understand.
你是说我必须选择
Are you saying I have to choose
崔妮蒂是死是活吗
whether Trinity lives or dies?
不  你已经做了选择
No, you've already made the choice.
现在你要理解它
Now you have to understand it.
不
No.
我不能这么做  我不会
I can't do that. I won't.
-你必须这样  -为什么
- Well, you have to. - Why?
因为你是救世主
Because you're the One.
要是我不能呢
What if I can't?
要是我失败了会怎样
What happens if I fail?
锡安会陷落
Then Zion will fall.
时间到了  听我的  尼奥
Our time is up. Listen to me, Neo.
你要是能到达源头  就能拯救锡安
You can save Zion if you reach the source,
不过你要先找到开锁匠
but to do that you will need the Keymaker.
开锁匠
The Keymaker?
是的  他不久前消失了
Yes. He disappeared sometime ago.
我们最近才知道他的下落
We didn't know what happened to him until now.
他被一个非常危险的程序囚禁起来了
He's being held prisoner by a very dangerous program...
一个最古老的程序  名叫梅洛文基恩
one of the oldest of us. He is called the Merovingian.
-他不愿放他走  -他想要什么
- And he won't let him go willingly. - What does he want?
有权力的人想要什么  更大的权力
What do all men with power want? More power.
准时到那儿
Be there at that exact time...
你就有机会
and you will have a chance.
我们得走了
We must go.
好像每次见面  我只会给你坏消息
Seems like every time we meet I got nothing but bad news.
我非常抱歉  发自内心的
I'm sorry about that. I surely am.
但不管怎样
But for what it's worth...
你让我有了信心
you've made a believer out of me.
祝你好运  小伙子
Good luck, kiddo.
安德森先生
Mr. Anderson.
收到我的包裹了吗
Did you get my package?
-收到了  -那好
- Yeah. - Well, good.
-史密斯  -不管是谁  看代码都不像特工
- Smith? - Whoever it is, he's not reading like an agent.
-见到我吃惊吗  -不吃惊
- Surprised to see me? - No.
-那你知道了  -知道什么
- Then you're aware of it. - Of what?
我们的联系
Our connection.
我还不明白是怎么回事
I don't fully understand how it happened.
或许是你的一部分印在了我身上
Perhaps some part of you imprinted onto me...
替代或是复制了我的那部分
something overwritten or copied.
不过已经不重要了  重要的是
It is, at this point, irrelevant. What matters is...
任何事都有原因
that whatever happened, happened for a reason.
那原因是什么
And what reason is that?
我杀了你  安德森先生  我看着你死去
I killed you, Mr. Anderson. I watched you die.
我得说当时还挺满足
With a certain satisfaction, I might add.
然后诡异的事发生了
And then something happened,
我知道那是不可能的
something that I knew was impossible...
可它确实发生了
but it happened anyway.
你毁灭了我  安德森先生
You destroyed me, Mr. Anderson.
后来呢  我知道规则
Afterward, I knew the rules,
我知道自己该做什么
I understood what I was supposed to do...
但我没做
but I didn't.
我做不到  我被迫留下来
I couldn't. I was compelled to stay...
被迫违抗指令
compelled to disobey.
我现在能站在这是因为你  安德森先生
And now, here I stand because of you, Mr. Anderson.
因为你  我不再是系统里的特工
Because of you, I'm no longer an agent of this system.
因为你  我改变了  拔掉了插头
Because of you, I've changed. I'm unplugged.
可以说焕然一新  跟你一样  自由了
A new man, so to speak. Like you, apparently free.
恭喜了
Congratulations.
谢谢
Thank you.
但你也知道  外表会欺骗你的眼睛
But as you well know, appearances can be deceiving...
所以又回到了我们来这的原因
which brings me back to the reason why we're here.
我们来这  不是因为我们是自由的
We're not here because we're free.
而是因为我们不自由
We're here because we are not free.
这事实无可逃避  否认也没有意义[目的]
There's no escaping reason, no denying purpose.
因为我们都知道  我们的存在
Because as we both know, without purpose...
-离不开目的  -是目的创造了我们
- we would not exist. - It is purpose that created us.
是目的联系着我们
Purpose that connects us.
是目的吸引着我们
Purpose that pulls us.
-指导着我们  -驱使着我们
- That guides us. - That drives us.
-是目的定义了我们  -让我们无法分离
- It is purpose that defines. - Purpose that binds us.
我们因你而来  安德森先生
We are here because of you, Mr. Anderson.
我们要从你身上拿走
We're here to take from you
你试图从我们身上拿走的东西
what you tried to take from us:
目的
Purpose.
-他怎么了  -不知道
- What's happening to him? - Don't know.
就是这样  很快就结束了
Yes, that's it. It'll be over soon.
-你  -对  是我
- You. - Yes, me.
我  我  我
Me, me, me.
还是我
Me too.
还不够
More.
你逃不掉的
It is inevitable.
加油  快出来
Come on, get out of there.
你没事吧
Are you all right?
-是史密斯  -是的
- It was Smith. - Yes.
-还不只一个史密斯  -很多
- Now there's more than one of them? - A lot more.
-这怎么可能  -我不知道
- How is that possible? - I don't know.
他好像找到了复制自己的方法
Somehow, he's found a way to copy himself.
他是要把你变成他吗
Is that what he was doing to you?
我不知道他要做什么
I don't know what he was doing...
-但我知道那是什么感觉  -什么感觉
- but I know what it felt like. - What?
感觉仿佛回到了那个走廊
It felt like I was back in that hallway.
死亡的感觉
It felt like dying.
机器在向下挖掘  躲避我们的防御系统
The machines are tunneling to avoid our defense system.
他们一定会占领
But I believe they're going to
某些管线的交汇处  以便控制管线
intersect certain pipelines in order to control them.
这些交点十分重要
These points of intersection are crucial...
因为我们很容易夺回来
because I believe they're vulnerable to counterattack.
虽然有人说
Although it has been suggested
这次攻击和我们多年来
that this is the same kind of attack...
遭受的袭击没什么两样
we've defended for years,
我敦促议会认清现实
I urge the Council to realize the truth.
这是我们有史以来面临的最大威胁
This is the single greatest threat we have ever faced...
如果不妥善应对  就无法生存
and if we do not act accordingly, we will not survive.
洛克指挥官  议会清楚这次攻击的严重性
Commander Lock, the Council is well aware of the seriousness of this attack.
我们准许你采取任何措施
You have our leave to prepare
准备防御工事
our defense by any and all means necessary.
-谢谢议会  -不过
- Thank you, Council. - However...
我们想知道有没有尼布甲尼撒号的消息
we ask if there's been word from the Nebuchadnezzar.
没有  议员  一点消息也没有
No, councillor. No word. Nothing.
那么我们要求派一艘船去
Then we request a ship be
探明救世主的下落
dispatched to ascertain the fate of the One.
可惜不可以  议员
I wish that were possible, councillor,
如果再少一艘飞船
but I do not believe our defense...
我们的防御系统会承受不住
can suffer the loss of another ship.
如果必须这样做  就能承受得住
It will, commander, if it must.
一艘飞船找尼布甲尼撒号要花好几天
It could take one ship days to find the Nebuchadnezzar.
-那就派两艘去  -这太疯狂了
- Then send two. - This is insane.
当心  指挥官
Careful, commander.
请原谅我的沮丧  议员
Forgive my frustration, councillors.
但我希望我能
But I wish I were able to
理解议会在这件事上的选择
comprehend the Council's choice in this matter.
合作的前提并不是理解
Comprehension is not a requisite of cooperation.
如果你要求我命令两位舰长
If you are asking me to order two of my captains...
没必要命令
There's no need for such an order.
舰长们都在场  他们可以自己回答
The captains are present. They can answer for themselves.
议会现征集
The Council is calling for
两位志愿者去援救尼布甲尼撒号
two volunteers to aid the Nebuchadnezzar.
哪两位愿意响应号召
Are there two among you that would answer such a call?
警戒号的舰长索伦
Captain Soren of the Vigilant
愿响应议会号召
will answer the Council's call.
你明白目前的形势吧  索伦舰长
You understand the situation, Captain Soren?
-是的  女士  -谢谢  舰长
- Yes, ma'am. - Thank you, captain.
还有吗
Is there another?
舰长  我们应该请愿
Captain, I think we should volunteer.
什么  你疯了吧
What? You have gone crazy.
-听我说  -闭上你的臭嘴  贝恩
- Listen... - Shut your hole, Bane...
不然要你好看
before I put you in one.
没有其他人了吗
Is there no other?
如果不明就里
Be hard for any man to risk his life...
不会有人愿冒生命危险的
especially if he doesn't understand the reason.
罗果斯号的舰长奈奥比
Captain Niobe of the Logos
愿响应议会号召
will answer the councillor's call.
-什么  -谢谢你  奈奥比舰长
- What? - Thank you, Captain Niobe.
洛克指挥官  有人接受你命令了
Commander Lock, you have your orders.
本次议事到此结束
This Council is hereby adjourned.
-奈奥比  你干什么  -我在尽力
- Niobe, what are you doing? - What I can.
为什么
Why?
因为世上有些事不会变  杰森
Because some things never change, Jason...
但有些事会变
and some things do.
你能看到什么  尼奥
What can you see, Neo?
很奇怪  代码好像不一样了
It's strange. The code is somehow different.
-加密了  -可能吧
- Encrypted? - Maybe.
这对我们是好是坏
Is that good for us or bad for us?
好像每层楼都布上了炸药
Well, it looks like every floor is wired with explosives.
看来不好
Bad for us.
我们走
Here we go.
是的  我们来找梅洛文基恩
Yes. We are here to speak with the Merovingian.
好的  他在等你们
Well, of course. He has been expecting you.
跟我来
Follow me.
我们的救世主尼奥终于来了
Here he is at last. Neo, the One himself.
是吧
Right?
还有传说中的墨菲斯
And the legendary Morpheus.
当然还有崔妮蒂  久仰大名
And Trinity, of course. I have heard so much.
真是蓬荜生辉啊  请坐
You honor me. Please, sit.
这是我妻子波塞芬
Join us. This is my wife, Persephone.
来点食物  酒水
Something to eat? Drink?
当然食物酒水都是假的
Of course, such things are contrivances,
跟这里一样
like so much here.
只是一副皮囊
For the sake of appearances.
-不用了  谢谢  -也是  谁有时间
- No, thank you. - Yes, of course. Who has time?
谁有时间
Who has time?
可要是我们不花时间
But then, if we do not ever take time,
又怎么会有时间
how can we ever have time?
1959年的侯伯王  上等葡萄酒
Chateau Haut-Briond, 1959. Magnificent wine.
我像热爱法语一样喜爱法国葡萄酒
I love French wine like I love the French language.
我尝试过各种语言
I have sampled every language.
法语是我的最爱  美妙无比
French is my favorite. Fantastic language...
尤其是说脏话
especially to curse with.
就像用丝绸擦屁股一样  我爱死它了
You see? It's like wiping your ass with silk. I love it.
你知道我们来这的目的
You know why we are here.
我贩卖信息
I am a trafficker of information.
能打探到的事我都知道
I know everything I can.
问题是  你们知道自己来这的目的吗
The question is, do you know why you are here?
我们来找开锁匠
We are looking for the Keymaker.
对  没错  开锁匠  当然
Oh, yes, it is true. The Keymaker, of course.
但这不是原因  也不是问题
But this is not a reason, this is not a why.
本质上来说  开锁匠
The Keymaker himself, his very nature,
是一种手段  不是目的
is a means, it is not an end.
所以找他
And so to look for him
是利用他做什么
is to be looking for a means to do what?
你知道问题的答案
You know the answer to that question.
但你知道吗
But do you?
你以为你知道  可其实你不知道
You think you do, but you do not.
你是受人指派而来
You are here because you were sent here.
有人要你来  你服从了而已
You were told to come here, and then you obeyed.
这是万物运作的规律
It is, of course, the way of all things.
只有一件事亘古不变
You see, there is only one constant...
四海皆准  这是唯一的真理
one universal. It is the only real truth.
因果关系
Causality.
作用  反作用
Action, reaction.
-原因  结果  -万事始于选择
- Cause and effect. - Everything begins with choice.
不  错
No. Wrong.
选择是有权力的人给没有权力的人
Choice is an illusion created between those with power...
创造的幻像
and those without.
看那位女郎
Look there at that woman.
天哪  看看她
My God, just look at her...
影响着周围所有人
affecting everyone around her.
毫不掩饰  香艳却又乏味
So obvious, so bourgeois, so boring.
但是等等
But wait.
我给她送了块甜点
Watch. You see, I have sent her a dessert...
一块特制的甜点
A very special dessert.
我亲自编写的
I wrote it myself.
开头非常简单
It starts so simply...
每行代码都是一种新感觉
each line of the program creating a new effect,
就像诗歌
just like poetry.
起初
First...
一阵燥热  她的心开始颤抖
A rush, heat. Her heart flutters.
尼奥  你能看到  对吗
You can see it, Neo, yes?
她不知道为什么会这样
She does not understand why.
是葡萄酒吗  不是
Is it the wine? No.
那是什么  原因是什么
What is it then? What is the reason?
很快这就不重要了
And soon it does not matter.
很快原因就会消失
Soon the why and the reason are gone...
只剩下那种感觉
and all that matters is the feeling itself.
这就是宇宙的本质
And this is the nature of the universe.
我们奋力反抗  我们奋力拒绝
We struggle against it, we fight to deny it...
但那都是假像  是谎言
but it is, of course, pretense. It is a lie.
我们外表镇定
Beneath our poised appearance...
内心其实已经完全
the truth is, we are completely...
失去控制
out of control.
因果关系  想逃也逃不掉
Causality. There is no escape from it.
我们永远是因果的奴隶
We are forever slaves to it.
我们心中仅存的希望和安宁
Our only hope, our only peace,
就是理解它  理解为什么
is to understand it, to understand the why.
"为什么"就是我们和他们
"Why" is what separates us from them...
你和我的不同
you from me.
"为什么"是权力的唯一来源
"Why" is the only real source of power.
没有它  你就无能为力
Without it, you are powerless.
所以你们来找我
And this is how you come to me,
不知道为什么  就没有权力
without why, without power.
环环相扣
Another link in the chain.
不过别怕
But fear not.
因为我知道你有多擅长服从命令
Since I have seen how good you are at following orders...
所以我会告诉你接下来做什么
I will tell you what to do next.
回去告诉那个算命的
Run back and give the fortuneteller this message:
她的时间快到了
Her time is almost up.
现在我有正事要办
Now I have some real business to do,
我要说再见了
so I will say adieu and goodbye.
-我们还没完事  -完事了
- This isn't over. - Oh, yes, it is.
开锁匠是我的
The Keymaker is mine,
我没有理由交给你
and I see no reason why I should give him up.
-毫无理由  -你要去哪儿
- No reason at all. - Where are you going?
亲爱的  我都说过了
Please, ma cherie, I have told you.
我们都是因果关系的受害者
We are all victims of causality.
我喝了太多红酒  要去撒尿
I drank too much wine, I must take a piss.
因果关系  再会
Cause and effect. Au revoir.
敢碰我就废了你的手
Touch me and that hand will never touch anything again.
不怎么顺利啊
Well, that didn't go so well.
你确定先知没跟你说别的吗
Are you certain the Oracle didn't say anything else?
-没有  -也许我们做错了什么
- Yes. - Maybe we did something wrong.
或是没做什么
Or didn't do something.
不  事已至此
No, what happened happened
走到这步都是必然
and couldn't have happened any other way.
-你怎么知道  -因为我们还活着
- How do you know? - We are still alive.
想找开锁匠  就跟我来
If you want the Keymaker, follow me.
出去
Get out.
我受够了他一串接一串的谎言
I am so sick and tired of his bullshit. On and on.
自大的混蛋
Pompous prick.
很久前  我们刚来的时候  不是这个样子
A long time ago, when we first came here, it was so different.
他也不是这个样子
He was so different.
他那时就像你
He was like you.
我会给你你想要的
I'll give you what you want,
但你也得给我一样东西
but you have to give me something.
-什么东西  -一个吻
- What? - A kiss.
你说什么
Excuse me?
我要你像吻她一样吻我
I want you to kiss me as if you were kissing her.
-为什么  -你爱她  她也爱你
- Why? - You love her. She loves you.
你俩坠入了爱河
It's all over you both.
很久以前  我也有过这种感受
A long time ago, I knew what that felt like.
我想记住这种感觉
I want to remember it.
我想体验一下  仅此而已
I want to sample it. That's all.
只是体验一下
Just a sample.
-要不你体验下这个  -崔妮蒂
- Why don't you sample this instead? - Trinity.
这么点事就大动肝火  只不过是个吻
Such emotion over something so small. It's just a kiss.
我们为什么要信你
Why should we trust you?
如果我不把开锁匠交给你们
If I don't deliver you to the Keymaker,
她可以杀了我
she can kill me.
好吧
All right.
但是你要让我相信  我就是她
But you have to make me believe I am her.
好吧
All right.
烂透了  算了吧
Terrible. Forget it.
等等
Wait.
好吧
Okay.
没错
Yes.
就是这种感觉
That's it.
我嫉妒你  可美好的事注定不会长久
I envy you. But such a thing is not meant to last.
跟我来
Come with me.
又来
Not again.
没事的  他们是我带来的
It's all right, boys. They're with me.
这两个给我丈夫干活
These fellas work for my husband.
专做见不得人的事  很忠实
They do his dirty work. They're very good, very loyal.
对吧
Aren't you, boys?
是的  夫人
Yes, mistress.
他们来自很早以前的矩阵
They come from a much older version of the Matrix.
但是跟那时的很多程序一样
But like so many back then,
他们惹的麻烦比解决的多
they caused more problems than they solved.
我丈夫还留着他们是因为
My husband saved them because
他们是出了名的难解决
they're notoriously difficult to terminate.
还有多少人会在枪里装银子弹呢
How many people keep silver bullets in their gun?
你要么跑去餐厅
You can either run to the restaurant
告诉我丈夫我干了什么
and tell my husband what I have done
要么待在这等死
or you can stay there and die.
他在女厕所
He's in the ladies' room!
快点
Hurry.
-我叫尼奥  -我知道  我是开锁匠
- My name is Neo. - Yes. I'm the Keymaker.
我一直在等你
I've been waiting for you.
天啊  天啊  波塞芬
My God! My God, Persephone,
你怎么能这样  你居然背叛我
how could you do this? You betray me.
-因果关系  亲爱的  -因果
- Cause and effect, my love. - Cause?
哪里来的因  什么原因
There is no cause for this. What cause?
什么原因  你身上的口红算不算
What cause? How about the lipstick you're still wearing?
口红  口红
Lipstick? Lipstick.
你在说什么疯话啊  女人
What craziness are you talking about, woman?
哪有什么口红
There is no lipstick!
她可没亲你的脸  亲爱的
She wasn't kissing your face, my love.
女人  这根本没什么
Woman, this is nothing.
-游戏而已  只是玩玩  -我这也是
- It is a game. It is only a game. - So is this.
玩地开心
Have fun.
好吧
All right.
来看看会发生什么吧
Let us find out where this goes.
你们俩  去抓开锁匠
You two, get the Keymaker.
这招挺不错
That's a nice trick.
我不能回去
I cannot go back.
我来搞定他们
I'll handle them.
搞定我们  你搞定我们
Handle us? You'll handle us?
你的前辈们可有礼貌的多
You know, your predecessors had much more respect.
好吧  算你有点本事
Okay, you have some skill.
干掉他
Kill him.
看到了吧  他也是个凡人
You see? He's just a man.
天杀的  你这个婆娘是要玩死我
Goddamn it, woman, you will be the end of me.
记着我的话  小伙子  好好记着
Mark my words, boy, and mark them well.
你那么多前辈都没干掉我  你也休想
I have survived your predecessors, and I will survive you.
-你去哪  -其他的路  总有其他的路
- Where are you going? - Another way. Always another way.
关门  快
Close it, quick!
可以快点吗
Could we move along?
跑
Run!
离门远点
Step away from the door.
那几枪算你头上
We owe you for that.
跟没事一样
Just like new.
把武器放下
Drop your weapon.
-你跟着他  -那尼奥呢
- Stay with him. - What about Neo?
他自己能搞定
He can handle himself.
坐到后面
Get in back.
该死
Shit.
-接线员  -林克  我在哪
- Operator. - Link, where am I?
你不会相信的  你在深山里
You'll never believe this, but you're all the way up in the mountains.
-是吗  -我得花上一会才能找到出口
- Really? - Yeah, it'll take me a while to get an exit.
-该死  -怎么了
- Oh, shit! - What?
那对双胞胎在追墨菲斯和崔妮蒂
Those twins things are after Morpheus and Trinity.
我没办法救他们出来
And I don't have a way to get them out.
-他们在哪  -城中央  南边500英里
- Where are they? - Middle of the city, 500 miles due south.
-接线员  -把我们弄出去  林克
- Operator. - Get us out of here, Link.
-这可不容易  长官  -我知道  我们在核心网里
- That won't be easy, sir. - I know. We're inside the core network.
是的  你附近的唯一出口在温斯洛天桥
Yes, sir. The only exit I got near you is the Winslow overpass.
-高速公路那里  -是的
- Off the freeway. - Yes, sir.
-好吧  我们会去的  -长官  我该说
- Fine, we'll make it. - Sir, I think I should say...
该死  小心后面
Oh, shit! Look out behind you!
-他要开枪了  -趴下
- Incoming fire. - Down!
坐好了
Hold on!
不好  事态恶化得太快了
Oh, no. This is getting real ugly real fast.
你在看吗  林克
Are you watching this, Link?
是的  长官  你们处境堪忧
Yes, sir. There's an all points on you.
有八辆警车朝你们开去
Eight units headed your way.
有什么建议吗
Any suggestions?
-右转  -这里右转
- Turn right. - Right, now.
这里直走就到连接101高速的隧道了
Straight here. You'll hit a connecting tunnel to the 101.
-知道了  -长官  你确定要这么做吗
- Got it. - Sir, are you sure about this?
我是说走高速  这太危险了
The freeway, I mean. It's dangerous.
我做了14年接线员  从来没见过
In 14 years of operating, I've never seen...
林克  我是怎么跟你说的
Link, what did I tell you?
明白  长官  我相信你  温斯洛天桥
Yes, sir. I do, sir. Winslow overpass.
-我会准备好的  -好样的
- I'll be ready for you. - Good man.
你一直叫我远离高速
You always told me to stay off the freeway.
-没错  -你说那是自杀
- Yes, that's true. - You said it was suicide.
那就祈祷
Then let us hope
我说错了吧
that I was wrong.
-接线员  -林克  我是奈奥比
- Operator. - Link, it's Niobe.
议会派我们来接你们
We've been sent to bring you in.
我要跟墨菲斯讲话
I need to talk to Morpheus.
相信我  奈奥比  他需要你
Believe me, Niobe, he needs you.
-他在哪  -跟着警笛走就对了
- Where is he? - Just follow the sirens.
重复  他们接近
Repeat, they're approaching the...
-追上他们了  -流亡程序是首要目标
- We have them now. - The exile is the primary target.
发生枪战
Shots fired.
开快点
Move!
-我们可生气了  -是的呢
- We are getting aggravated. - Yes, we are.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
带他走
Get him out of here.
快点
Come on!
撞死他
Crush him.
墨菲斯
Morpheus.
他没事  你们快走
He's okay. Keep moving.
我们走
Let's go.
我需要接线启动摩托车的程序
I need a download to hot-wire a motorcycle.
没问题  摩托车速成班
No problem. One crash course on motorcycle...
等一下
Wait.
不用了
Cancel that.
你还真厉害
You are handy.
上车
Jump on.
-她一点用也没有  -寻找流亡程序
- She means nothing. - Find the exile.
找到了
We have them.
1-A-12  收到请回复
One-Adam-twelve, please respond,
趴下
Get down.
接住了
Gotcha.
她还真厉害
She's good.
你已经没用了
You are no longer necessary.
我们只做自己该做的事
We do only what we're meant to do.
你只该做一件事  被删除
Then you are meant for one more thing: deletion.
踹飞他
Go kick his ass.
尼奥  你要是在的话  快帮我一把
Neo, if you're out there, I could use some help.
那是什么
What is that?
欧耶  欧耶
Yes! Yes!
长官  伊卡洛斯号已确认
Sir, we have confirmation from the Icarus.
前两艘飞船已做好反击准备
First two ships are in position for counterattack.
很好
Good.
有什么变化吗
Any change?
它们钻到了铁矿  减慢了点速度
They hit some iron ore here. Slowed them down a little.
-迟了多少  -也许一个小时吧
- How much? - An hour, maybe.
那就还有九个小时多一点
That would give them a little over nine hours.
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
有一栋楼
There is a building,
楼里面
inside this building,
有那么一层  电梯上不去
there is a level where no elevator can go
楼梯也进不到
and no stair can reach.
那层楼里满是门  这些门通往很多地方
This level is filled with doors, These doors lead to many places,
很多隐藏的地方
hidden places.
但是有一扇门很特别
But one door is special.
那扇门通往源头
One door leads to the source.
这栋楼有周密的系统保护着
This building is protected by a very secure system.
触发警报就会引爆炸弹
Every alarm triggers the bomb.
炸弹  他刚才是说炸弹吗
Bomb? Did he say bomb?
但像所有系统一样  它也有弱点
But like all systems, it has a weakness.
这系统也要依靠大楼
The system is based on the rules of a building.
-环环相扣  -电力
- One system built on another. - Electricity.
一环断掉  后面的全部失效
If one fails, so must the other.
没有电也就没有警报
No electricity, no alarms.
但是要给这样一座大楼断电
But you'd have to take out a city block
得切断整个街区的电
to kill the power to a building like that.
-不止一个  27个  -27个街区
- Not one, 27. - Twenty-seven blocks?
有一座电站
There is a power station,
必须毁掉
it must be destroyed.
可是肯定会有备用供电系统
There must be some kind of fail-safe.
没错  是有个应急系统
Yes, there is an emergency system.
必须进到电力系统的核心
The core network of the grid must be accessed,
关闭应急系统
the emergency system must be deactivated.
那你要我们干什么
Then what do you need us for?
那两个系统尼奥可以随手关掉
Neo could take them both out easier than we could.
-时间不够  -为什么
- There's no time. - Why?
一旦门的保护解除  连接就断开了
Once the door is unprotected, the connection will be severed.
但是必须要先建立起另一个连接
But another connection must first be made.
-需要多久  -整整314秒
- How long will that take? - Exactly 314 seconds.
五分钟多一点
Just over five minutes.
你们只有这么久
That is the length and breadth of the window.
只有救世主才能打开那扇门
Only the One can open the door...
也必须在这段时间内打开
and only during that window can the door be opened.
你怎么会知道这些
How do you know all this?
因为我必须知道  这是我存在的目的
I know because I must know. It is my purpose.
是我在这的原因
It's the reason I'm here,
也是我们在这的原因
the same reason we're all here.
尼奥  我知道你有心事
Neo, I know something's wrong.
你不用告诉我
You don't have to tell me.
我只想告诉你  我在你身边
I just want you to know that I'm here.
大家必须统一步调
All must be done as one.
戴上也无妨
Can't hurt.
一招棋错
If one fails,
满盘皆输
all fail.
午夜时分
At midnight, there is a
两栋大厦的保安都会换班
shift change in the security of both buildings.
我们就在午夜动手
At midnight, we will strike.
要睡回家睡
You count sheep at home.
为什么  在这睡还有钱拿
Why? I get paid to count them here.
好了  他们进去了
Okay, they're inside.
-有多长时间  -12分钟
- How much time? - Twelve minutes.
该死
Oh, shit.
我们这辈子  都在打这场战争
All of our lives, we have fought this war.
相信今晚  我们能结束战争
Tonight, I believe we can end it.
今晚不是意外
Tonight is not an accident.
这世界上没有意外
There are no accidents.
我们走到这一步也不是机缘巧合
We have not come here by chance.
我不相信机缘
I do not believe in chance.
但我看到三个目标  三名舰长  三艘飞船时
When I see three objectives, three captains, three ships
我看到的不是巧合  而是天意
I do not see coincidence. I see providence.
我看到了目的
I see purpose.
我相信我们注定来到这里  这是我们的命运
I believe it is our fate to be here. It is our destiny.
我相信今晚就是我们每个人
I believe this night holds for each and every one of us
存在的意义
the very meaning of our lives.
我想请你答应我件事  但我不知怎么说
I want to ask you to do something, but I don't know how.
只要我做得到  我都答应你
I promise you, if I can, I will.
要是我想让你无论如何
What if I asked you to stay out of this
都不要参与
no matter what
不进到矩阵里呢
to stay out of the Matrix?
为什么
Why?
求你了
Please.
好吧
All right.
怎么了  奈奥比
What is it, Niobe?
我不禁会想  墨菲斯
I can't help it, Morpheus.
我不禁会想  万一你错了呢
I can't help thinking, what if you're wrong?
要是这预言  这一切都是狗屁呢
What if all this, the prophecy, everything, is bullshit?
那也许明天我们都会死
Then tomorrow we may all be dead.
但我们本来就一直命悬一线
But how would that be different from any other day?
这是场战争  我们是战士
This is a war, and we are soldiers.
任何时间  任何地点
Death can come for us at any time,
我们都可能牺牲
in any place.
敌人入侵  敌人入侵
Incoming. Incoming!
敌    人    接    近
敌人入侵
Incoming!
再考虑一下另外一种可能性
Now consider the alternative.
要是我说对了呢  预言是真的呢
What if I am right? What if the prophecy is true?
要是明天战争就能结束呢
What if tomorrow the war could be over?
难道不值得我们为之抗争吗
Isn't that worth fighting for?
不值得我们为之牺牲吗
Isn't that worth dying for?
-时间  -三分钟
- Time? - Three minutes.
马上就好
Almost there.
做好了
It is done.
找一下其他人
Find the others.
找到奈奥比了  他们已经出了电站
I got Niobe there. They're already out of the station.
-索伦呢  -找到了
- What about Soren? - There.
他们还在里面  但是
They're still inside, but...
他们不动了
They're not moving.
时间到了  出发
That's it, let's go.
马上打给尼奥
Call Neo now.
-找不到他们了  他们已经进去了  -电网呢
- I lost them. They're inside the portal. - What about the grid?
紧 急 系 统 启 动
还在正常运转
Everything is still operational.
应急供电系统开始恢复供电了
The emergency system is already rerouting power.
天啊
Jesus.
他们一开门  就全完了
Soon as they open that door, it's all over.
完不了
The hell it is.
你想  崔妮蒂
What are you...? Trinity!
我绝不会在这袖手旁观
I will not stand here and do nothing.
也绝不会眼睁睁地看他们送死
I will not wait here and watch them die.
崔妮蒂  只剩不到五分钟时间了
Trinity, we're talking less than five minutes here.
五分钟足够我炸毁大楼了
In five minutes, I'll tear that whole goddamn building down.
-还有多远  -快了  就快到了
- How much further? - Here, just here.
非常抱歉  此路不通
I'm sorry, this is a dead end.
这绝对是最险的一次
It's gotta be the ugliest hack I have ever done.
我只能送你到这了
That's as close as I can get you.
你最好长翅膀飞过去
You better grow some wings.
-接线员  -我进来了
- Operator. - I'm in.
继续走  65楼
Keep moving. Sixty-fifth floor.
再见到我你好像很吃惊  安德森先生
You look surprised to see me again, Mr. Anderson.
我却不一样
Well, that's the difference between us.
我可是盼着你来
I have been expecting you.
-你要干什么  史密斯  -你还没想明白吗
- What do you want, Smith? - You haven't figured that out?
这么久了还是想不到点子上
Still using all the muscles except the one that matters.
我和你要的一样
I want exactly what you want.
我什么都要
I want everything.
要不要来一发子弹
Would that include a bullet from this gun?
来吧  尽管开枪
Go ahead, shoot.
我最大的优点  就是有好多个我
The best thing about being me, there's so many me's.
天哪  这是怎么了
Christ! What the hell happened in here?
站住  小姑娘
Hold it right there, little lady.
打不过我们
If you can't beat us...
就加入我们
Join us.
墨菲斯
Morpheus!
输 入 密 码
允许访问
还是没发现他们
Still no sight of them.
我不知道他们在做什么  但只剩两分钟了
I don't know what they are doing but they only got two minutes left.
█
禁用 电力
禁用 电力 节
█
禁用 电力 节点
是否确定 是/否
错误  应急系统失效
供电中断
一分钟
One minute.
供电中断
快啊
Come on.
拜托了
Please.
杀了他们
Kill them.
他们进去了
They're in.
难以置信
I don't believe it.
这是注定的
It was meant to be.
墨菲斯  那扇门会送你回家
Morpheus, that door will take you home.
你知道走哪扇门  快去  尼奥
You will know which door. Hurry, Neo.
崔妮蒂  有特工在向你靠近
Trinity, I got some serious activity headed your way.
你好  尼奥
Hello, Neo.
-你是谁  -我是架构师
- Who are you? - I am the Architect.
矩阵就是我的作品  我一直在等你
I created the Matrix. I've been waiting for you.
你有好多疑问
You have many questions.
虽然做了救世主  你的意识变化很大
Though the process has altered your consciousness,
但你依然是人类
you remain irrevocably human.
因此  我的回答
Ergo, some of my answers
你只能明白其中一部分
you will understand and some of them you will not.
有趣的是
Concordantly,
你的第一个问题  既是最要紧的
while your first question may be the most pertinent,
可你也许意识不到  它也是最无关的
you may or may not realize it is also the most irrelevant.
我为什么在这
Why am I here?
你的存在  汇集了矩阵编程时产生的
Your life is the sum of a remainder of an unbalanced equation
所有不平衡因素
inherent to the programming of the Matrix.
你是程序异常的产物
You are the eventuality of an anomaly,
我竭尽全力
which despite my sincerest efforts,
还是不能消除这些异常
I've been unable to eliminate from what is otherwise,
达到数学上的完美和谐
a harmony of mathematical precision.
虽然我极力避免产生异常
While it remains a burden assiduously avoided...
却也做了准备
it is not unexpected
因此你的到来
and thus not beyond a measure of control,
也完全在我的
which has led you, inexorably,
掌控之中
here.
-你答非所问  -非常正确
- You haven't answered my question. - Quite right.
有意思  比其他人快多了
Interesting. That was quicker than the others.
其他人  有多少  什么其他人
Others? How many? What others?
矩阵的历史远比你了解的久远
The Matrix is older than you know.
我倾向以两次异常之间的间隔
I prefer counting from the emergence of one integral anomaly
来划分版本
to the emergence of the next.
也就是说  现在的矩阵是第六版
In which case, this is the sixth version.
我之前还有五个  撒谎  胡扯
Five before me? He's lying! Bullshit!
可能的解释只有两种
There are only two possible explanations.
在我之前居然还有五个
There were five before me.
要么没人告诉我
Either no one told me,
-要么没人知道  -没错
- or no one knows. - Precisely.
你应该也想明白了
As you are undoubtedly gathering,
这异常是系统性的
the anomaly is systemic,
最简单的等式也会产生偏差
creating fluctuations in even the most simplistic equations.
你休想控制我  看老子碾碎你
You can't control me! I'm gonna smash you to bits!
我要宰了你
I'm gonna fucking kill you!
你控制不了我  白毛老混蛋
You can't make me do anything, you old, white prick!
选择
Choice.
问题在于选择
The problem is choice.
我设计的第一版矩阵十分完美
The first Matrix I designed was quite naturally perfect,
是一件艺术品
it was a work of art.
完美无缺
Flawless, sublime.
它的伟大
A triumph equaled
配得上后来惨痛的失败
only by its monumental failure.
我已经明白  这不可避免的毁灭
The inevitability of its doom is apparent to me now
是人类固有的缺陷导致的
as a consequence of the imperfection inherent in every human being.
因此我研究你们的历史  重新设计
Thus, I redesigned it based on your history
以更准确地反映出
to more accurately reflect
你们诸多荒唐的天性
the varying grotesqueries of your nature.
但最终的崩溃使我再次失望
However, I was again frustrated by failure.
之后我逐渐明白  要解决我的问题
I have since come to understand that the answer eluded me
要设计出更弱的意识
because it required a lesser mind.
或者说  不那么完美的意识
Or perhaps, a mind less bound by the parameters of perfection.
另一个程序无意间找到了答案
Thus, the answer was stumbled upon by another,
是个直觉程序
an intuitive program,
用来研究人类心智的
initially created to investigate certain aspects of the human psyche.
如果我是矩阵之父
If I am the father of the Matrix,
那她无疑是矩阵之母
she would undoubtedly be its mother.
-先知  -别这么叫
- The Oracle. - Please.
我说了  她只是偶然间发现了
As I was saying, she stumbled upon a solution
只要给他们选择  近99%的测试对象
whereby nearly 99 percent of all test subjects accepted the program,
都会接受命运
as long as they were given a choice,
哪怕他们只是
even if they were only
隐约地感觉自己有选择权
aware of the choice at a near unconscious level.
这一方案虽然有效
While this answer functioned,
缺陷也很明显
it was obviously fundamentally flawed,
因此产生了与之对立的系统性异常
thus creating the otherwise contradictory systemic anomaly,
如果不加管控  必将危及整个系统
that, if left unchecked, might threaten the system itself.
那些拒绝接受系统的人
Ergo, those that refused the program,
虽然数量不多  但越晚处理
while a minority, if unchecked,
就越可能引发灾难性后果
would constitute an escalating probability of disaster.
你是在说锡安
This is about Zion.
你来这是因为锡安即将毁灭
You are here because Zion is about to be destroyed.
每一名居民都将被消灭
Its every living inhabitant terminated,
整座城市夷为平地
its entire existence eradicated.
胡扯
Bullshit.
人类的反应中  否定最容易预见
Denial is the most predictable of all human responses.
但不用慌张
But rest assured,
这将是我们第六次摧毁锡安
this will be the sixth time we have destroyed it,
这次我们更加轻车熟路了
and we have become exceedingly efficient at it.
救世主的作用
The function of the One
就是在此时返回源头
is now to return to the source,
将你身上的部分代码
allowing a temporary dissemination of the code you carry,
重新注入主程序
reinserting the prime program.
之后  你必须从矩阵中选择23个人
After which you will be required to select from the Matrix 23 individuals,
16名女性  7名男性  重建锡安
sixteen female, seven male, to rebuild Zion.
如果不这样做
Failure to comply with this process
系统会出现灾难性崩溃
will result in a cataclysmic system crash,
杀死所有与矩阵连接的人
killing everyone connected to the Matrix,
再加上锡安的毁灭
which, coupled with the extermination of Zion,
人类将彻底灭绝
will ultimately result in the extinction of the entire human race.
你不会允许这样的
You won't let it happen. You can't.
你们靠人类生存
You need human beings to survive.
我们能应对各种恶劣的生存条件
There are levels of survival we are prepared to accept.
不过关键是  你准备好承担
However the relevant issue is whether or not you are ready
毁灭全人类的责任了吗
to accept responsibility for the death of every human being in this world.
观察你的反应真是有趣
It is interesting reading your reactions.
你的五位前辈
Your five predecessors were,
均是基于对反应的预测设计的
by design, based on a similar predication,
这先入为主的设定
a contingent affirmation
让他们对其他人类
that was meant to create a profound attachment
产生了眷恋
to the rest of your species,
促使他们履行救世主的义务
facilitating the function of the One.
其他几位救世主的眷恋是广义的
While the others experience this in a general way,
你的却具体得多
your experience is far more specific,
也就是爱
vis-a-vis love.
崔妮蒂
Trinity!
她此时恰好进入了矩阵
Apropos, she entered the Matrix
甘冒生命危险  拯救你的性命
to save your life at the cost of her own.
不
No.
揭示真相的时刻终于到来了
Which brings us at last to the moment of truth,
系统的终极缺陷展露无遗
wherein the fundamental flaw is ultimately expressed
而这次的系统异常
and the anomaly revealed
会终结现在  开启未来
as both beginning and end.
这里有两扇门
There are two doors.
你右手边的门
The door to your right
通往源头  可以拯救锡安
leads to the source and the salvation of Zion.
左手边的门能带你回到矩阵  去找她
The door to your left leads back to the Matrix, to her,
但人类也将随之灭亡
and to the end of your species.
你之前说的很好  问题就在于选择
As you adequately put, the problem is choice.
但我们都知道你会怎么选  是不是
But we already know what you are going to do, don't we?
我能看到你头脑里的连锁反应
Already I can see the chain reaction,
化学物质触发了一系列电信号
the chemical precursors that signal,
产生了一种
the onset of an emotion
可以压倒逻辑和理性的情绪
designed specifically to overwhelm logic and reason.
而这种情绪
An emotion that is already
蒙蔽了你的双眼  对真相视而不见
blinding you from the simple and obvious truth:
她必死无疑  而你无能为力
She is going to die and there is nothing you can do to stop it.
希望  是人类最典型的臆想
Hope. It is the quintessential human delusion,
既是你们的力量之源
simultaneously the source of your greatest strength
也是你们的致命弱点
and your greatest weakness.
如果我是你  我会希望不要再见
If I were you, I would hope that we don't meet again.
不会了
We won't.
碰上大麻烦了  长官
We got a serious situation, sir.
糟了
Oh, no.
那是什么
What was that?
反正我从没见过这么快的东西
Whatever it is, it's moving faster than anything I've seen.
天哪  他接住她了
Holy shit, he caught her.
尼奥  我必须来
Neo, I had to.
我明白
I know.
子弹还在里面
The bullet is still inside.
崔妮蒂
Trinity,
你千万别放弃
don't you quit on me now.
抱歉了
I'm sorry.
崔妮蒂
Trinity.
Trinity,
我知道你听得见
I know you can hear me.
我不会放弃的
I'm not letting go.
我做不到
I can't.
我实在太爱你了
I love you too damn much.
太神奇了
I can't take this.
这下我们扯平了吧
I guess this makes us even.
我不明白
I don't understand it.
该做的都做了
Everything was done as it was supposed to be done.
救世主回到了源头  战争就应该结束
Once the One reaches the source, the war should be over.
-24小时内会结束的  -什么
- In 24 hours, it will be. - What?
如果24小时内我们再不行动
If we don't do something in 24 hours,
锡安就会被毁灭
Zion will be destroyed.
-什么  -你怎么知道
- What? - How do you know that?
-有人告诉我的  -谁
- I was told it would happen. - By whom?
是谁不重要  我相信他
It doesn't matter. I believed him.
不可能  预言说...
Impossible. The prophecy tells us...
预言是假的  墨菲斯
It was a lie, Morpheus.
预言是假的
The prophecy was a lie.
救世主什么都结束不了
The One was never meant to end anything.
只是机器的另一种控制行为
It was all another system of control.
我不相信
I don't believe that.
你自己也说了
But you said it yourself.
如果战争没结束  预言怎么会成真
How can the prophecy be true if the war isn't over?
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我知道这很难接受
I know it isn't easy to hear, but...
但我保证我说了实话
I swear to you it's the truth.
-我们该怎么办  -我不知道
- What are we gonna do? - I don't know.
坏了
Oh, no!
-他们在干什么  -恰好在EMP范围之外
- What are they doing? - They're just out of EMP range.
是炸弹
It's a bomb.
我们得赶紧撤离
We have to get out of here. Now.
我做过一个梦
I have dreamed a dream,
但那个梦已经离我远去
but now that dream has gone from me.
它们来了
Here they come.
快走  墨菲斯
Let's go, Morpheus.
-我们逃不掉了  -那也要试试
- We won't make it. - We have to try.
-快过来  -不对劲
- Come on! - Something's different.
什么
What?
我能感觉到它们
I can feel them.
尼奥
Neo!
-发生什么了  -不知道
- What happened? - I don't know.
是汉默号
It's the Hammer.
他陷入了某种昏迷
He's in some kind of coma,
但体征很稳定
but his vitals are stable.
你怎么样
What about you?
我很好
I'm fine.
你最好休息一下
You could use some rest.
不  我要陪着他
No, I'm gonna stay with him.
洛克说对了
Lock was right.
他预判到机器会切断进出锡安的主管线
He guessed that the machines would cut off the mainlines in and out of Zion.
反击会让它们措手不及
He thought a counterattack might surprise them.
听上去挺好  我也以为能成
It sounded good. I figured we had a shot,
但有人搞砸了
until someone screwed it up.
大家还没就位  就有人释放了EMP
An EMP was triggered before we got in position.
当时就毁灭了五艘飞船
Five ships were instantly downed.
等到机器大军攻过来时
When the machines broke through,
已经不是战斗了  而是屠杀
it wasn't a battle, it was a slaughter.
是技术事故吗  飞船出故障了
Was it an accident? Some sort of malfunction?
-谁知道呢  -有人知道
- No one knows. - Someone does.
谁
Who?
机器大军取胜之后  就继续向下挖掘了
Once the machines were done with us, they started digging again.
我们经过时搜了一下幸存者
We made a quick pass to look for survivors.
找到了吗
You found one?
只有一个
Only one.